Bowen Xu

Residence: 393 Middle Huaxia Rd, Shanghai

E-mail: xubw1@shanghaitech.edu.cn * Telephone number: (+86) 18852719756

Place of birth: Yangzhou, Jiangsu, China * Date of birth: 2002-08-16

Personal Profile

Senior, Major in Computer Science (CS)

Mentor: Ziyu Shao

 $\textbf{Research Interests:} \ \ \textbf{Bandit} \ \& \ (\textbf{Deep}) \ \ \textbf{Reinforcement Learning}, \ \textbf{Network Intelligence}, \ \textbf{Online Learning}$

and Optimization, Deep Learning with Principled Design.

Personal Website: xubowen0816.github.io/bowen-xu.github.io/.

Education

ShanghaiTech University (Co-Founded by the Chinese Academy of Sciences)

Sep 2020 - Jun 2024 (Expected)

- Undergraduate; School of Information Science and Technology.
- **GPA:** (Graduate courses) 4.0 / 4.0; (Junior) 4.0 / 4.0; (Overall) 3.8 / 4.0.
- Major Ranking: Top 1 in 3 out of first 6 semesters; (Overall) 12 / 177, top 6%.
- **Honors:** Merit Student (top 3%, 2021, 2023), Outstanding Student (top 7-8%, 2022).

Curriculum

- Mathematics: Convex Optimization (Graduate course, A+) / Matrix Computations (Graduate course, A+) / Numerical Optimization (A+) / Mathematical Analysis I (A) / Mathematical Analysis II (A) / Linear Algebra (A).
- Major: Reinforcement Learning (Graduate course, A+) / Deep Learning (Graduate course, A) / Online Optimization and Learning (Graduate course, A) / Computer Architecture I Project (A+) / Artificial Intelligence I (A).

Research Experience

At Network Intelligence Center (NICE), ShanghaiTech University, Shanghai, China. Jan, 2022 - Present

Constrained Personalized Federated Learning (to be submitted for ICML-2024)

Position: Main Researcher

Apr 2023 - Present

- Design an innovative algorithm framework combining online feedback (in particular, bandit feedback) and supervised feedback to solve the complex task of integrating online learning with offline machine learning.
- Apply this framework in federated distillation systems to solve the online client selection problem with constrained resources in wireless communication tasks between an edge server and edge clients.
- Conduct code simulation experiments and excel in federated distillation systems, using the MNIST handwritten dataset for recognition as the machine learning task of the edge clients.
- Achieve theoretical guarantees and obtain superior numerical performance of this algorithm framework through the Lyapunov optimization technique.

Constrained GNN Bandit Algorithm with Social Network (to be submitted for ICML-2024)

May 2023 - Present

Position: Project Leader

- Combine GNN (Graph Neural Network) and Bandit algorithm to solve the client selection task in graph structure problems.
- Design a novel GNN-Based Primal-Dual algorithm to address resource-constrained client selection problems involving graph structures, particularly in social network scenarios.
- Obtain theoretical guarantees and numerical performance of GNN-Based Primal-Dual algorithm through GNTK (Graph Neural Tangent Kernel), Lyapunov optimization and Virtual Queuing.
- Conduct code simulation experiments and excel in resource-constrained client selection problem with graph structures.

AI for Science by Deep Reinforcement Learning

Apr 2023 - Present

Position: Project Leader

- Apply deep reinforcement learning algorithm (Monte Carlo Tree Search) in protein design projects to help design protein structures with specific properties and geometric constraints.
- Innovate the network structure based on the classical deep reinforcement learning network in AlphaZero through techniques such as Squeeze-and-Excitation Block. And obtain relatively better performance compared with traditional networks.

Penalty PPO Algorithm

Nov 2022 - Jan 2023

Position: Project Leader

- Introduce the Penalty Function Method and Sample-Based Estimation to the PPO algorithm to solve the bias in the estimation of the value function caused by the inappropriate step size.
- Conduct code simulation experiments by using the Pendulum environment in the gym package to test our algorithm and achieve better results compared with the classical PPO algorithm.

Honors and Awards

- Merit Student (top 3%), ShanghaiTech University, 2021.
- Merit Student (top 3%), ShanghaiTech University, 2023.
- Outstanding Student (top 7-8%), Shanghai Tech University, 2022.
- Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM): Honorable Mention, 2022.
- Mathematics Competition of Chinese College Students: Second Prize, 2021.
- Mathematics Competition of Chinese College Students: Third Prize, 2022.
- Mathematics Competition of Shanghai College Students: Second Prize, 2021.
- Mathematics Competition of Shanghai College Students: Third Prize, 2022.
- National Collegiate Mathematics Competition Network Challenge: Third Prize, 2022.

Teaching Assistantship

Mathematical Analysis II (Head TA) Probability and Statistics for EECS

Feb 2022 - Jun 2022 Feb 2023 - Present

- Organized teaching assistant work & carried out online teaching.
- Weekly in-person tutorial and after-class questions (including exercise & discussion sessions).
- Designed and graded assignments (including weekly assignments, course projects, exam papers).

Activities

- Social Practice, Group Leader (Outstanding Individual Award), Gansu, 2021.
- Artificial Intelligence Industrial Practice (Outstanding Team Award), Shanghai, 2022.

Technical skills

Programming Languages/Tools English Proficiency C, C++, Python(Pytorch), Matlab, LAT_EX, etc. TOEFL iBT: 100 (Writing Score: 28).